Guide to the Maurice J. Valency Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Maurice J. Valency Papers
1945-1963.
Valency, Maurice Jacques, 1903-
1.5 linear ft. (3 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079425
Maurice Valency was a mid 20th Century playwright working in New York City. This collection contains manuscripts of articles, plays, teleplays, librettos, and the first draft of the book, The Flower and the Castle: An Introduction to Modern Drama, written by Valency.
Biographical Note
Maurice Valency (1903-1996) was an American playwright, critic, author, and translator. Valency was born March 22, 1903 in New York City and was educated at the City College of New York and Columbia University.
Valency was a professor of comparative literature at Columbia University and taught dramatic literature at Julliard (where he also served as their director of academic studies) and Brooklyn College.
Valency was most active as a playwright in the 1940s and 1950s with such works as Ondine, The Madwoman of Chaillot (both adaptations from French dramatist Jean Giraudoux), The Visit (adapted from Swiss dramatist Friedrich Duerrenmatt), and La Perichole (adapted from German-born French composer Jacques Offenbach's opera bouffe).
Valency was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1960, which he used to complete his study of modern drama, The Flower and the Castle. Other awards and fellowships include a Ford Foundation Fellowship in 1958, The New York Drama Critics Circle Award for best foreign play in 1949 for his adaptation of The Madwoman of Chaillot by Jean Giraudoux, the New York Drama Critics Circle Award for best foreign play in 1954 for his adaptation of Ondine by Jean Giraudoux, and the New York Drama Critics Circle Award for best foreign play in 1959 for his adaptation of The Visit by Friedrich Duerrenmatt. The Visit also was nominated for a Tony Award for Best Play in 1959.
Maurice Valency died on September 28, 1996.
Scope and Content
Collection is comprised primarily of scripts and manuscripts of plays and adaptations written by Valency. Prominent among the manuscripts are the scripts of his celebrated English versions of Jean Giraudoux's The Madwoman of Chaillot and Ondine, both of which contain his autograph corrections and emendations, as well as the script for the opera bouffe, La Perichole, which was performed during the New York Metropolitan Opera's 1956-1957 season. Also present in the collection are scripts and manuscripts of Valency's The Apollo of Bellac, The Thracian Horses, A Double Life, The Better Half, a German adaptation of Valency's The Thracian Horses for Swiss television, as well as newspaper and magazine clippings, telegrams, and the typescript, bearing autograph notations, of Valency's study of modern drama entitled The Flower and the Castle, which was published in 1963.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series:
Series I: Maurice Valency Scripts and Manuscripts
Subjects
Giraudoux, Jean, 1882-1944.; Offenbach, Jacques, 1819-1880.; Ritchard, Cyril, 1897-1977.; Valency, Maurice, 1903-1996.; Columbia University--Faculty.; Giraudoux, Jean, 1882-1944.; Literature, Comparative--Study and teaching.; French literature.; Drama.; Literature--Adaptations.; Scripts.; Autographs.; College teachers.; Dramatists.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
1968 M-68 Valency, Maurice J. Gift
- Series I: Maurice Valency Scripts and Manuscripts, 1945-1963
  - The Apollo of Bellac, Television Script, Second Revision, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    English adaptation of a Jean Giraudoux play. Aired as a part of the Ford Foundation's Television-Radio Workshop magazine series, Omnibus. Contains handwritten corrections, emendations. (Two copies)
  - Battleship Bismarck
    - Script, First Revision, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Contains handwritten corrections, emendations.
    - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Magazine Articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manuscripts B-E, 1956-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Better Half, Script, Final Revised Draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - A Double Life, Television Script, First Draft, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Aired as a part of Showcase Productions' Aloha Hour. Contains handwritten corrections, emendations.
  - The Enchanted, Script, Rehearsal Copy, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    English adaptation of a Jean Giraudoux play. Contains handwritten corrections, emendations.
  - Manuscripts E-F, 1953-1954, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Excursion #18, Television Script, Final, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Aired as a part of the Ford Foundation's Television-Radio Workshop magazine series, Omnibus. Contains handwritten corrections, emendations.
  - Feathertop, Television Script, First Draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Based on a story by Nathaniel Hawthorne. Contains handwritten corrections, emendations.
  - The Flower and the Castle: An Introduction to Modern Drama, Manuscript, Original Draft, undated (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 5 to 7)
  - Manuscripts G-L, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gina, Script, First Draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Long Night, Script, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Co-written with Leo Lania. Contains handwritten corrections, emendations.
  - The Madwoman of Chaillot
    English adaptation of a Jean Giraudoux play.
    - Script, First Draft, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Script, Rehearsal Copy, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letter from Herbert Myron, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ondine, Script, Rehearsal Copy, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - La Perichole, 1956, 1957 (5 Folders)
    English adaptation of the Jacques Offenbach opera bouffe.
    - Script, First Revision, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Script, Rehearsal Copy, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Rehearsal Schedule, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "French Without Tears", Magazine Article for Opera News, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "The Little Coach that isn't There", Magazine Article for Metropolitan, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1956, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Telegrams, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Score, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Copy of the 1868 Jacques Offenbach and Leon Roques score to La Perichole in French. Valency's English adaptation is handwritten on the score, 1956.
  - The Queen's Gambit
    - Script, Rehearsal Copy, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - 8:40 in Little Theatres in New York, Vol. 2, No. 10, June 1955 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Reluctant Virgin
    - 1948 (2 Folders). (Box 3, Folder 18 to 19)
      English adaptation of a Carlo Gozzi play.
    - Script, First Revised Draft, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Script, Rehearsal Copy, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - The Second Stranger, undated (2 Folders)
    Based on a Thomas Hardy story.
    - Television Script, First Draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Television Script, First Revised Draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Thracian Horses, Script, Rehearsal Copy,1948 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Manuscripts T-V, 1955, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Toine, Television Script, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    English adaptation of a Guy de Maupassant play.
  - The Virtuous Island, Script, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Die Wilden Pferde, Television Script, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Walther Franke-Ruta's German adaptation of Valency's The Thracian Horses for the Swiss Broadcasting Corporation.
  - Letter from Heiner Gautschy of the Swiss Broadcasting Corporation (Box 3, Folder 23)